<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Seeds from the Apple of Discord</title>
    <description>Johanna Appel&#39;s notes about the world, science &amp; technology, programming, languages, music, art, learning and absurdities.
</description>
    <link>https://malumdiscordi.ae/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://malumdiscordi.ae/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 28 Dec 2015 15:19:25 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 28 Dec 2015 15:19:25 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.0.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Instruction Leaflet</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;About this blog, the weather, me and the meaning of life&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In absence of a better idea of splitting things up, I’ll use this as a general brain and idea dump for everything and nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what you can and will find here is stuff that I personally considered interesting, thought provoking, funny, smart or otherwise worthwhile posting - which probably involves techy and nerdy topics, as well as philosophical discussions, general scientific considerations, languages, music, arts, learning and absurdities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some things I definitively plan to write about: Free, Libre and Open-Source Projects, Operating Systems and the Usage of Computers in General, Programming Languages, -Paradigms and -Concepts (and how all that stuff relates to the industry), Sentient Machines and the Future of Humanity, Insights from a Modern (digital &amp;amp; non-digital) Life, and How to Get Along With People…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So, who am I?&lt;/strong&gt; (no, this is not the meaning of life part yet, hang tight)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I consider myself an all-time student of everything…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, more seriously, I spend most of my time either working on software projects for clients - I’m a self-acclaimed expert in all things Scala/JVM and backend API related - or with my colleagues from &lt;a href=&quot;http://innoki.de&quot;&gt;INNOKI&lt;/a&gt; where we facilitate innovative workmodes in big and small teams and enterprises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from that, my other aspirations go more into the direction of research and science: Personally, I find it far more rewarding and motivating to get to know and understand the world, compared to earning, managing and spending money - as most of my fellow humans seem to enjoy these days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alright, but what about the weather and that meaning of life thingy?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also like rhetoric questions and weird humor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;~ Johanna&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 28 Dec 2015 14:41:33 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://malumdiscordi.ae/2015/12/28/instruction-leaflet.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://malumdiscordi.ae/2015/12/28/instruction-leaflet.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
